Hi everyone, this
is a lecture on
atherosclerosis and
ischemic heart disease.
It used to be a two hour
lecture with myocardial
infarction being part of
it. And now we've kind of
split it into two. So the
second part will be myocardial
infarction and ischemic
heart disease. So there's
gonna be a lot of overlap
and some repetition.
And I think repetition
is good because
it helps things
stick in your head.
So these are the session
objectives that you can read
on your own. And if you
want to keep track, this is
an outline overview of what
we're going to go over.
Now, I want to make sure
that you understand that
atherosclerosis is a
type of arteriosclerosis.
Arteriosclerosis just
means hard arteries.
Sclero means hard. So
there's going to be wall
thickening of the
arteries and loss of
elasticity. And generally
speaking, under the term
arteriosclerosis is
arteriosclerosis, Mockenberg
medial sclerosis which only
affects the medial layer,
and something called
fibromuscular intimal
hyperplasia. I'm just going
to introduce those, I'm not
going to test you on those
three, but the concept
here that we're going to
talk about much more into
detail is atherosclerosis.
So first let me quickly
go through the
arteriosclerosis where you have
narrowing of small arterioles.
You will learn this more
in the renal part of the
course. You get hyaline
arterial sclerosis.
Hyaline just means pink and
glassy, like this vessel
here looks like pink and
homogenous, because protein
leaks into the wall. And
this is common in hypertension
and type 2 diabetes.
What we're going to
learn also in the kiddie
section is that
there's hyperplastic
arteriosclerosis, where it
looks like an onion ring.
There's thickening of
the vessel wall. There's
hyperplasia of the
smooth muscle. And this
is from malignant
hypertension, which has nothing
to do with cancer, but
how high hypertension
can get. And you have
the onion skinning.
Mockenberg's medial
calcific sclerosis.
First thing I want
to tell you is
this is clinically
not significant.
It's just something
you can see and just be
aware of. This breast
mammogram here shows
kind of a pipe stem
appearance. It is not
anything to worry about,
but it's just calcification
of the media of the
muscular arteries.
And then there's fibromuscular
intimal hyperplasia,
which is really something
that's driven by inflammation
or mechanical injury. It's
like a healing response,
and you see that a lot
when stents restenose. That
is a different thing than
fibromuscular dysplasia,
which you're going to learn
about when you learn about
renal stenosis. So those
are things for the future.
Here is where we really
want to start. That's why
there's the big red star
there, atherosclerosis. And
this is the whole pathology
that is important because
it's responsible for the
heart, the brain, and
peripheral vascular disease,
coronary disease, strokes,
etc.
What arteries get
affected? mostly the
abdominal aorta, the
coronary arteries,
and the popular teal
arteries, the internal carotid
arteries, and the circle
of Willis. Doesn't
mean any others can't be,
but those are the main
ones. And what happens
is that the intima, as
you remember, there are
three layers to a vessel,
adventitia media intima,
the inner layer becomes
thickened, and there's a
plaque that we'll talk about
that obstructs the blood
flow. So the vessel itself,
the blood flow, is narrowed
or completely occluded.
In doing so, the
media is also weakened
and that's something
else to keep in mind.
When we talk about atheromas,
those are the intimal
lesions. The other words
for that is atheromatous
or atherosclerotic plaques
and they protrude into
the vessel lumen. So the
big thing here to take away
is that there's intimal
thickening and lipid accumulation
and atherosclerosis
and these are just some
cartoons in a normal
picture one on the top is a
cartoon of what an atheroma
or an atherosclerotic plaque
looks like it's raised
it's focal and it starts
within the intima that's
important to know it has a
soft yellow core of lipid
that's usually mostly
cholesterol and it's covered
by a fibrous cap. And as
you can tell, the cartoon
is very, you know, bright
and it has different colors,
but on the bottom it's
kind of subtle. But it's
showing you the pale pink
areas that are the
atherosclerosis,
the atheromatous parts.
So there's three major
parts to an atheroma, and
that is the cells, the
extracellular matrix,
and the lipid. The
cells are smooth muscle,
macrophages, and mostly T
lymphocytes or white cells.
And the extracellular matrix
is made up of collagen
and elastic fibers and
proteoglycans. And of
course, the whole big thing
here is lipids, whether it
be intracellular and
extracellular. Don't worry
too much about the staining
here. This is just, the
top one is macrophage
staining, so it's nice and
brown. And that shows how
many macrophages are within
the intima. And on the
bottom is a smooth muscle
stain which shows you the
fibrous cap a little bit
that as it's outlined in
like a blue gold color.
So let's talk about
some risk factors for
atherosclerosis.
Again the rest of this
lecture is on atherosclerosis.
Modifiable things are
things like smoking
and hypertension and
hyperlipidemia because
you can do things like
stop smoking and watch
your diet and things
like that. diabetes.
Systemic inflammation is an
important thing. Inflammation
is a big thing when it
comes to atherosclerosis.
There's something called C
-reactive protein, and it's
an acute phase reactant
that comes from the liver.
It's an independent marker
of risk for myocardial
infarction, stroke,
peripheral artery disease, and
sudden cardiac death. The
higher it is, the more
likely the risk. There is
some limited evidence that
certain bacteria or
viruses may be evolved in
the pathogenesis. Again,
that's circumstantial. That's
not hard evidence. That's
CMV, chlamydia, etc.
Non-modifiable risk
factors include the age,
your sex, which is increased
in men, the atherosclerosis
risk, and post
-menopausal women because
estrogen is protective
in pre-menopausal women.
They say sex is non
-modifiable because that means
the sex you're born with,
but we know nowadays that
can be changed but it doesn't
change the risk really.
Family history is very
important. If you have a family
history that's an independent
risk factor and of
course genetic issues such
as mutations in your LDL
receptor gene and something
called homocystinuria.
What happens is this is an
inborn error metabolism and
because of it you get
increase in homocysteine which
is hyperhomocystinemia.
And when that happens,
there's an association with
premature vascular disease,
coronary atherosclerosis,
stroke, etc.
All the things that
are listed there.
Okay, so let's start with
the atherogen. How do
these atheromas begin? The
model right now, and what
everybody pretty much
embraces, is a response
to injury. There's chronic
inflammation and there's
a healing response of
the arterial wall that is
initiated by endothelial
injury. So the first thing
is you got to have
endothelial injury. What
causes endothelial injury?
Well a lot of things can.
Hypercholesterolemia because
they believe too much
cholesterol will impair the
endothelial cell function
because it increases local
reactive oxygen species. There's
also different hemodynamic
effects for example
hypertension if you have
hypertension that directly
increases the shear stress the
hemodynamic shear stress on
the endothelial cells also if
there's areas of disturbance
or turbulent blood flow
so you will see more
plaques especially at
bifurcations and things like that
laminar blood flow just
means you know smooth lamina
means plate so smooth you
know on on turbulent or non
-turbulent blood flow protects
against atherosclerosis.
Inflammation is a big
thing, and inflammation
is triggered because
of cholesterol crystal
accumulation and free
fatty acids in the
macrophages. And of course,
chronic diseases are
contributory, hypertension,
diabetes, obesity.
Okay, so, oh, went the
wrong way. Sorry about that.
So again, this is just
to rehash the response to
injury theory. Chronic
endothelial injury needs
to happen for
atherosclerosis to begin, for
the pathogenesis to occur,
and these are just the
same things I just
mentioned that may lead to
chronic endothelial injury.
They're listed here.
Okay let me just talk a little
bit about hypercholesterolemia
because that's one of
the factors listed.
LDL is mostly cholesterol
and when you have chronic
hypercholesterolemia that
can, as I mentioned earlier
cause endothelial dysfunction
because it produces
oxygen free radicals.
The lipoproteins will
accumulate in the intima and
what happens is interestingly
is the LDL in the
macrophages are oxidized by
free radical generation and
then they're engulfed by
macrophages via a scavenger
receptor and they become
what are known as foam
cells which we'll go into.
The inflammation is
important in atherosclerosis
because as I said earlier it's
triggered by the accumulation
of cholesterol crystals
that's a repeat from what
I said before and the
dysfunctional endothelial cells
would do express surface
selective adhesion molecules
and that's important
because that will bind white
cells particularly monocytes
and T lymphocytes now
remember monocytes are
peripheral blood once they're
in tissue we call the
macrophages so keep that in mind
monocytes will stick to
the endothelium then they
kind of migrate into the
intima, the inner layer of the
vessel of the artery, and
then they change or transform
to macrophages, which
will engulf oxidized LDL.
Those macrophages are
then called foam cells.
You get a progressive
accumulation of lipids.
Macrophages themselves
will produce
things like interleukin
-1 and TNF, etc.
And the T-cells, the C
-lymphocytes and monocytes also
interact with cytokines.
So basically what you have
is a chronic inflammatory
state, which has been
initiated by endothelial injury
or damage. This is a really
important, although busy,
slide from Robbins. It's
how an atheroma develops.
And you kind of got to go
from upper left to right.
Over here, if you see my
arrow, these are things
that can cause, as we went
through, endothelial injury
and dysfunction. function,
and then you get, these
are the monocytes that come
and kind of stick to the
endothelium and then go
through the endothelium,
and here is the, they become
macrophages once they're
in tissue, and you have,
they have to be oxidized,
the lipids have to be
oxidized, and these are
the foam cells that result,
and then in time we get
proliferation of smooth
muscle cells, and we'll
talk more about this when we
talk about progression of it,
but this This is basically
the visual of what I
just kept talking about.
So the overview of what
happens as the atherosclerotic
plaque develops, I'm
going to say verbally
but then I have some really
good pictures to help.
Again and I am repeating
myself and I can't emphasize
more that endothelial
injury is very important
because that will increase
permeability, the chance
that the white blood cells
will adhere, and also
exposure to thrombogenic
agents. If you remember from
thrombosis lectures, you
know, once the endothelium
is exposed, you've got
platelets will aggregate.
You have the accumulation
of lipoproteins,
as I mentioned,
monocytes going, again,
this is repetitive
adhere to the endothelium
and become foam cells
within the intima.
And the important thing
then is that factors that
come from the activated
platelets and the macrophages
and the vascular cells
cause the smooth muscle
cells to migrate. They
actually move from the
media to the intima and they
proliferate in the intima
and produce extracellular
matrix. So you've got
collagen and proteoglycans
that accumulate and this
is as a plaque becomes
more and more mature this
is the development of the
progression and there's
also recruitment of T
cells and lipid continues
to accumulate it could be
extracellular within the
macrophages or it also
could be intracellular and
later later later you may
develop calcification and
that's very severe and
you'll see what I mean in a
couple of slides so what
I just said now we can go
through again, but with
visualization. And I know that's
being repetitive, but I
want to just get the point
across. This is from
Robbins, and it's really kind
of nice because there's
like, there's steps here.
And first you have the
endothelial damage, and it
lists the chronic endothelial
injury things that we've
already talked about,
hypolipidemia, smoking, etc.
And so once there's damage
and the lipids are high in
the blood they leak into
the intima because of the
endothelial dysfunction and
that's the step number two.
I mean again this
is kind of it's kind
of artificial to make
them steps but this
is kind of a nice
way to remember them.
So then the macrophages
once the monocytes get into
the intima the macrophages
are activated and the
vascular smooth muscle
cells move to the intima and
you see that in the bottom
picture with those smooth
muscle cells going into
the intima and you have
some macrophages which are
the foam cells. This is
usually mediated by growth
factors such as PDGF and
FGF if you remember the
growth factors. Now we're not
done here there's more
there's steps four and five
again this is a false
kind of they're not really
set there there it's a
spectrum but I just want it
it's easier to remember this
way. The lipid has to be
oxidized, as I mentioned,
for the macrophages to
actually take them up using
the scavenger receptor.
And so once that happens,
it becomes foam cells. And
the first thing you see,
and you see this even in
children, is the fatty streak,
which I'll have a picture
of later. And there's also
going to be platelet adhesion,
remember, because there's
been loss of integrity
of the endothelium. And
then this vascular smooth
muscle proliferation and the
formation of the atheroma.
So I have been repeating
myself, but I'm trying to
make a point here that
it's a developing process.
A word about this thing
I call the fibrous cap.
This is really dense collagen.
I mean, smooth muscle
that makes dense collagen,
and it establishes the
strength and the plaque
stability, which is very
important, and it undergoes
remodeling constantly.
um collagen is made by the
smooth muscle cells and
degraded by enzymes those enzymes
are called metallopropenases
and they come from
macrophages in the atheroma
and the presence of
inflammation destabilizes the
plaque integrity so why
am I telling you all this
well because this is
important in the maturation or
stabilization of a plaque
I mentioned that the smooth
muscle cells migrate and go
into the intima, proliferate,
etc. This is me repeating
myself again and the
growth factors that are
involved and this becomes a
stabilizing force for the
plaque. And so this is a nice
stable plaque here. We've
got a thick fibrous cap, a
little small lipid core,
not too much inflammation,
and increased proliferation
of student muscle cells.
This is stable because it
probably won't rupture.
It may cause stenosis as
you can tell the lumen is
stenotic, but the plaques
rupture when they just can't
stand the mechanical
stresses of the shear forces.
So what do I mean? Okay
so this is a nice real
picture of a stable fixed
plaque. You can even
see down here in the
purple area that's
calcification and this is
stable. It's not going to
rupture yet anyway and
it is stenotic. I mean,
this whole thing was
once a whole vessel, the
whole artery, and now
it's definitely narrowed.
What we want to talk
more about are the
unstable or the vulnerable
plaques. And these
are the plaques that
have a very thin fibrous
cap, meaning they have
few smooth muscles.
Their lipid core is very
large, and they have a lot
of inflammation. And the
inflammation will destabilize
the plaque, as I mentioned
earlier. so low levels of
smooth muscles it's just
not stable and and it's more
likely to rupture and
this is a cartoon of it so
this is a nice comparison
stable and stable pack a plaque
I just want you I think
it's important to realize
because it's the unstable
ruptured plaque that we worry
about when it comes to
unstable angina and myocardial
infarction again I want
to emphasize the large
lipid core, the thin fibrous
cap, a lot of macrophages,
there's going to be
hemorrhage and cap rupture can
be happening. And that maroon
thing is a superimposed
thrombus, which makes the
stenosis even worse. So
that's the difference
between the types of plaques.
And here is a beautiful
picture, I think, of the
vulnerable atherosclerotic
plaque with a clot there.
So again, you have
the large lipid core,
the fibrous cap was thin,
so there's not a lot of
smooth muscles, and you have
an increase in the matrix
metalloproteinases, which
is important because that's
part of the inflammation,
and that degrades things.
And usually it's a low-grade
stenosis. In other words,
it could be 30, 40, 50
percent stenosis. It doesn't
have to be a complete you
know, 70 or 90% stenosis.
It usually is a low-grade
stenosis when actually the
plaque ruptures. So let's
stop with a question about
a 70-year-old man. He goes
to the ER. He has slurred
speech and left arm weakness.
That begun two hours
ago. He has a past medical
history of hypertension,
does not smoke
currently, but did smoke.
He is on lisinopril, a
multivitamin. They hear
bruise over the carotid
arteries and the
physician suspects a stroke
and wants to do intermediate
intervention to
restore the blood flow.
The stroke, the physician
says, was most likely
caused by a clot that
traveled from the carotid
arteries and obstructed
blood flow into the
brain. Given most likely
cause, what microscopic
findings would be expected
to be found in this
patient's carotid artery.
So think about this.
The best answer here, think
about it. Thick fibrous
cap A is not correct because
that would mean there's
a stable plaque. I know we
were talking mostly about
the hearts, the coronary
arteries, but this is to,
we're looking at the carotid
arteries for a second.
So a thick fibrous cap would
be more stable. A small
lipid core would be more
stable and a low level
of inflammation would be
more of a stable because a
lot of inflammation may get
unstable. Now I did mention
low degree of stenosis
but really the best answer
here is D as in David low
levels of smooth muscle.
That's likely what made
this a vulnerable plaque
not the 30% stenosis
that's it may be 30 40
50 that's kind of up
in the air but the big
answer here is the low
levels of smooth muscle which
made this a vulnerable
plaque that ruptured
and then went to or the
blood you know you got a
clot that went to the
brain so the answer is d as
in david uh low levels of
smooth muscle this is a
special scene that kind
of shows you the evolution
of progression of a plaque
rupture or ulceration
again when there is more
inflammation there's more
likelihood of rupture and
that leads to thrombus
formation and that can
either embolize like it did
in the question before,
or obstruct blood flow.
And depending on what
organ is, you know, what
vessel and what organ,
we can end up with a
myocardial infarction,
a stroke, or chronic
kidney disease. And these
are just pictures of
one. They're kind of
neat because you see how
the plaque ruptures is
kind of in real time.
And C is really
kind of really nice
because they use
a special stain.
You know, the plaque
continues to progress. If it
doesn't rupture, there's
vessel narrowing obstruction
loss of elasticity and you
remember one thing that's
important is that
atherosclerosis because it causes
narrowing will promote
hypertension and hypertension
itself causes more endothelial
damage so you have a
vicious cycle there and more
damage leads to more plaque
formation which is why a lot
of people with hypertension
have atherosclerosis and
vice versa this you do
not have to memorize I just
wanted to I took it from
this was the old-fashioned way
they did the atherosclerosis
progression the point
being that you go from
type one to type six and
you get worse okay so you
can take a look at this and
you know we talk about fatty
streaks and complicated
lesions this is the progression
of atherosclerosis so I
earlier mentioned fatty
streaks and this is really
really subtle right here
is a little line here they
can be seen and they have
been seen in children
unfortunately who passed away
from some other disease or
were in car accidents and
they developed very very
early these fatty streaks.
Now myelethosclerosis is
shown on the left side
which is A which shows
some plaques and when you
get severe we are looking
at the arrows in B which
are ulcerated and even
one with an overlying
thrombus. So this is by the
way where we have opened
up and I should have
mentioned that on this slide
too. We have opened up
the aorta, the thoracic
aorta, and that's what
we're looking at once we
open it up longitudinally.
I like this picture just
because it shows the
difference between mild,
moderate, and severe, and
as you can tell, way on
top, it's going from bottom
to top. The severe is
horrible. I mean, if you
were to touch these with
gloved hands, there would
be a lot of hardness
because there's calcification
and there's thrombus.
So So it's really, again,
this is the opening of
the thoracic and abdominal
aorta longitudinally.
Let's do another question.
A 50-year-old man
has some episodes of
severe substernal chest
pain every time he does
some moderate exercise.
The episodes, though,
have become more frequent
and severe over the
year, but can be relieved
by nitroglycerin. He's
afebrile, his heart rate
is relatively normal
at 78, no murmurs, etc.
He has a normal serum
creatinine level, mildly
elevated glucose level,
mild to moderately elevated
cholesterol level. So
which of the following
cardiac lesions is most
likely to be present?
Hopefully you recognize that
what we're talking about
here is not an acute MI.
We didn't say anything
about, we didn't even talk
about MI yet. But the most
likely thing that this
person has with the elevated
glucose and the elevated
cholesterol and this substernal
chest pain is coronary
atherosclerosis. B, as in
boy, is the answer. And that
coronary atherosclerosis,
the narrowing of the
coronary arteries, have been
causing blood flow to be
decreased and ischemia to
occur and substernal chest
pain in the form of what we
call angina, whichever way
you want to pronounce it.
This is another picture.
I show this because you
can realize, you know, it
can get really stenotic.
Look at the microscopic
picture on the right.
There's very little room
there for blood to flow.
And the reason why I'm
showing you the picture on
the left is one is in the
fresh state, meaning it
was just cut, and one is
in the fixed state, it was
put in formalin. So I just
want you to get used as
different pictures on what
they look like. You can
see how yellow the atheromatous
plaque is, but when
you fix it with formalin,
it becomes more brown.
So what are the
complications? And these are
the things to worry about.
Rupture, ulceration,
erosion. These are
big, big problems.
Once this happens, that
can lead to thrombosis.
And once you have
thrombosis overlying a
plaque, you can get
possible complete occlusion.
It also can lead
to embolism and go
somewhere, like to the
brain or another organ.
The plaque can also
have hemorrhage
in it, and that
may be part of the
rupture or may even
extend the rupture.
Another complication is an
aneurysm. What does that
mean? The media, remember I
told you early on, is going
to be weakened. And so there's
going to be outpatching
of the vessel wall due
to weakness of the media.
The thickened intima
means that there's less
oxygen diffusion to the
rest of the vessel wall.
And little by little,
the media becomes
atrophic, and that causes the
weakening, and you
can get an aneurysm.
All right, so I've been
talking about atherosclerosis.
I mentioned a little
bit about it causing
stroke. But what we really
want to talk about, what
we're going to get to
here, is the angina or the
myocardial infarction.
We're worried about the
coronary arteries. It can
affect a lot of different
areas, as you can tell.
But we're worried about
the coronary arteries in
this particular lesson.
So clinically,
atherosclerosis will
develop slowly in coronary
arteries and are
usually asymptomatic
until about greater
than 70 to 75 percent
stenosis or thrombosis
or embolization occurs.
You know, that number,
77%, it's not that it's
debatable, but I've seen
different sources say different
things. But generally
speaking, that's when you
get the first real symptoms
of chest pain in the form
of angina. And that's what
I'm talking about, your
heart, angina, and if it's
very severe, obviously
for the next time we'll
talk about the myocardial
infarctions. And the other
organs that can be affected
by stroke, et cetera,
are listed here as well.
Okay, so just a review, and
this is important because
the coronary arteries from
anatomy, you know, you
dissected them, they feed
different parts of the
heart. And so this is a
review so you know that which
coronary, whatever coronary
artery is affected,
whether it be one, two, or
three, that's the part of
the heart that's going to
be losing blood or losing
oxygen, I should say. So the
big one, the left anterior
descending, it feeds the
apex of the heart, the
anterior wall of the left
ventricle, and the anterior
two-thirds of the ventricle
septum. This is just
review. The right coronary
artery is usually the
entire right ventricle, etc.
And then there's the left
circumflex, which only
perfuses the lateral wall.
If you remember, the
coronary artery that gives
rise to the posterior
descending branch is considered
the dominant side and
most people are right
dominant. That's again a
little bit of a review.
I'm telling you this
because the anatomy is
important as to what's going
to happen to the heart.
So most patients who
have what we know is
ischemic heart disease
have coronary artery
disease. That's why
they have ischemic heart
disease. They have
atherosclerosis usually
affecting one or even
more coronary arteries.
Now the stenosis can be
progressive so we have
a chronic or fixed
obstruction, or we can have
an acute change, an
acute plaque disruption
with superimposing thrombosis,
which is very sudden
and acute. I mentioned
the 70-75% stenosis.
That causes symptomatic
ischemia induced by
exercise. What does that
mean? That's stable angina.
That means somebody's
fine when they're sitting
down, but when they do
some moderate exercise,
they start getting
chest pain, a little bit
of chest pain. That is
not a myocardial infarct.
When you get 90% stenosis,
now you're talking
that even at rest, there's
going to be chest pain.
So these are just cartoons
showing, again, the
atherosclerosis. These
are just visualizations of
what I'm talking about.
Here's another question.
A 47-year-old man has
chest pain upon exertion.
He was well four months
ago, but he developed
chest discomfort while
jogging four months ago.
His symptoms have progressed
and that is a very
important point so that
now he has chest pain even
after climbing one flight
of stairs. He does have
diabetes controlled by
diet. He is a smoker.
His father and maternal
grandfather both died of
heart disease. That's
important for family history
especially because it
was before the age of 60.
Because of the patient's
chest pain he's put in the
hospital and he develops in
the fifth day chest pain with
mild activity, minimally
responsive to sublingual
nitroglycerin. The CKMB, even
if you don't know what it
is now, we'll talk about that
in myocardial infarction,
that's an enzyme. And even
if you don't know what it
is, you see that it's normal.
So if the CKMB is normal,
that means that there's no
cardiac muscle has died.
And the serum troponin is
the same thing. It's also
normal. So there has not
been death of myocardial
muscle. So it cannot
be an acute myocardial
infarction. That's not what
it is because we have normal
CKMB and troponin, which
we'll talk about more.
It's not a cardiac arrhythmia.
Dresser syndrome we'll talk
about in the next lecture.
This can't be stable engine,
and the reason why is
because it's progressive.
It's gotten worse, and now
he's sitting down and he's
having trouble and it's
only minimally responsive
to sublingual nitroglycerin.
So the answer is E as in
Edward, unstable angina.
So ischemic heart
disease, let's
just define
myocardial ischemia.
What we mean is that
the their supply
and demand of the
heart for oxygenated
blood is going
to be imbalanced.
The blood you know the heart
needs a lot of oxygen and
it gets it through blood
flow. When you reduce the
coronary blood flow because
of atherosclerotic obstruction
or coronary artery disease,
you will get ischemia.
So what does that mean?
Clinically, it means that
you develop angina pectoris
or angina pectoris,
which just means pain
of the chest, pectoris.
Usually this is less severe
ischemia and there's no
death of cardiac muscle. I
can't emphasize that enough.
Ischemia, there's no death,
okay? Once you have death
or necrosis of cardiac muscle,
remember we talked about
death in the first year,
that is a myocardial
infarction, and we'll talk
about that in the next lecture.
The other things that
can happen is chronic
ischemic heart disease,
and the person will
develop heart failure
or even sudden death.
So a little bit about
angina pectoris,
and we are going
to also repeat this
again so that
there'll be overlap.
These are known as sudden
recurrent attacks of chest
pain, usually underneath
the sternum or in front
of the heart precordial,
caused by transient, meaning
15 seconds to 15 minutes
ischemia of the heart.
There is no necrosis,
no infarct in an angina,
okay? That's important to
remember because once you
have infarct necrosis, we're
talking about a myocardial
infarct, we're talking
about a heart attack.
So stable or typical
angina means that
there's reduction of
coronary blood flow or
perfusion because of
either chronic stenosis
or whatever coronary
artery is affected.
It's usually not associated
with plaque disruption,
and often nitroglycerin, which
is a very good vasodilator,
will help relieve the
symptom. unstable angina
or sometimes called pre
-infarction angina is much
more serious what happens
is there's an increased
progressive frequency usually
it happens at rest it's more
prolonged and you can have
a partial you can have a
disruption of the plaque
with superimposed partial
thrombosis not complete
because if it's complete you're
gonna have blockage complete
blockage there's also
another one they discuss
which is Prince metal angina
which is really has to
do with coronary artery
spasm. This is very uncommon.
It is not a common thing.
It is not related
to the exercise
or blood pressure
or heart rate.
It also can be relieved by
nitroglycerin or calcium
channel blockers. Again,
it's not as common as the
other two. And this is kind
of a visual of what I've
just been saying. On the
left is a normal vessel.
As we move from the
left to the right we see
exertional angina which
is stable angina where the
arterial lumen is narrowed
by a stable plaque so there's
partial stenosis. The
one in the middle is the
vasospastic one. This can
happen with cocaine. It
can happen in other reasons
but it's inappropriate
vasoconstriction. Usually
there isn't a plaque.
Unstable angina is the next
one over and that means
the plaque has ruptured and
there has been formation
of a non-occlusive
that very important non
-occlusive thrombus because
once it's in occlusive as you
see all the way on the right
you've got an infarction
you've got cardiac arrest
you've got myocardial
infarction you've got a
heart attack so this is
just a table kind of
summarizing the difference in
the different anginas and
what's important and take
a look at this it's
important um sometimes you do
get in stable angina temporary
depression of st segment
I am not a cardiologist
nor do I read ekgs but
that has been mentioned
um although some you know
depending on what you read
you see different things
another question a 68 year
old obese woman presents
with substernal chest pain
and a history of recurrent
angina pectoris and
intermittent claudication,
meaning that she has
peripheral vascular
disease and every
so often she gets
cramps in her calves
or things like that.
She has an elevated CKMB
6.6, as you see the normal
0 to 5. Now, normals range,
you know, I think the
other normal was a little
bit different. Normals
range from lab to lab. The
point is this one is still
increased and the serum
troponin is up as well.
The EKG changes show ST
elevations. So which of the
following mechanisms is
most likely responsible?
It's not likely going to
be vasospasm that's going
to cause this because
vasospasm is intermittent and
it's not going to last
long enough to cause a
myocardial infarction unless
again it's cocaine induced
or something like that.
The best answer here is A,
coronary artery thrombosis.
What has happened is
that a plaque has ruptured,
a thrombosis has been
superimposed upon that
and completely occluded a
coronary artery causing
a myocardial infarction.
When we talk about acute
coronary syndrome, and
this is kind of as a lead
-in to the next lecture,
There are basically unstable
angina, acute myocardial
infarction, and sudden
cardiac death. Again,
abrupt atherosclerotic
plaque change,
rupture, followed by
thrombosis. That's
really the key here
to these syndromes.
The disruption of the
partially stenotic plaque
can happen by rupture,
erosion, or ulceration,
or hemorrhage. um
vasoconstriction they have
said that it may play a
role um in constricting
the lumen but um
again a vaso just
vasoconstriction without a
plaque is is not common um
so coronary thrombosis
most of the acute coronary
syndromes are associated
with disruption of
the vulnerable plaque the
atherosclerotic vulnerable
plaque it's not a stable
plaque, not fixed.
And the very important thing
to take away for now and
the next session is that
the myocardial function
often, why it occurs, is a
thrombus is superimposed on
a disrupted plaque, which
was previously only partially
stenotic. And that makes
a total occlusion so no
blood flow goes through. No
blood flow causes necrosis
of whatever area of the heart
as we learned the anatomy
is affected and we have
a myocardial infarction.
Many ruptured plaques
with the coronary
thrombosis that result in
MI occur when the
vessels or arteries are
only partially
somatic, many less than
70%. This is a nice
overview of the mechanism
of of coronary
thrombosis, and I put it
there for kind of an
organizational map.
This is a gross picture
of, again, this is
a coronary artery
that has been opened
longitudinally, and
you see a plaque with
superimposed thrombus,
and this caused an MI.
And this is a cross
-section if you didn't do it
longitudinally, so you have
a big thrombus basically
occluding a coronary artery
and causing an MI. So
these are the summary
slides. This is a summary
slide to take a look at
and the lecture feedback
form. I'd like to thank
Nicole Maddy who's in the
class 2024 who contributed
some pictures and if you
have any questions please
feel free to come by my
office to use Canvas or
email me in any way or come
by and I will give you
as much help as possible.
and thank you very
much for listening.